<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE module SYSTEM "https://corepunch.github.io/orca/schemas/module.dtd">
<module name="core" namespace="orca" on-luaopen="on_core_module_registered">
  <require file="../geometry/geometry.xml"/>
  <externals>
    <external struct="localization"/>
    <external struct="game"/>
    <external struct="Property"/>
    <external struct="lua_State"/>
    <external struct="style_class_selector"/>
    <external struct="style_rule"/>
  </externals>
  <enums>
    <enum name="MessageRouting">
      <summary>Defines the routing strategy for messages sent to objects. This determines how messages propagate through the object hierarchy and which handlers are invoked.</summary>
      <value name="Bubbling">Messages are bubbled up the hierarchy.</value>
      <value name="TunnelingBubbling">Messages are first tunneled down the hierarchy and then bubbled up.</value>
      <value name="Tunneling">Messages are tunneled down the hierarchy.</value>
      <value name="Direct">Messages are sent directly to the target object.</value>
    </enum>
    <enum name="PropertyState">
      <summary>Represents the various states a property can be in.</summary>
      <value name="Normal">Normal property state when no triggers are active</value>
      <value name="Hover">Property state when the mouse is hovering over it</value>
      <value name="Focus">Property state when it has focus</value>
      <value name="Select">Property state when it is selected</value>
      <value name="Disable">Property state when it is disabled</value>
      <value name="OldValue">Property state representing the previous value</value>
    </enum>
    <enum name="BindingMode">
      <summary>Various modes to bind properties</summary>
      <value name="OneWay">Default mode, updates target property when source changes</value>
      <value name="TwoWay">Updates target property when source changes and updates source when target changes</value>
      <value name="OneWayToSource">Updates source property when target changes, but not the other way around</value>
      <value name="Expression">Allows binding to a custom expression</value>
    </enum>
    <enum name="PropertyAttribute">
      <summary>Attributes that can be applied to properties for binding purposes.</summary>
      <value name="WholeProperty">Default binding to the whole property</value>
      <value name="ColorR">Bind to the red channel of a color property</value>
      <value name="ColorG">Bind to the green channel of a color property</value>
      <value name="ColorB">Bind to the blue channel of a color property</value>
      <value name="ColorA">Bind to the alpha channel of a color property</value>
      <value name="VectorX">Bind to the X component of a vector property</value>
      <value name="VectorY">Bind to the Y component of a vector property</value>
      <value name="VectorZ">Bind to the Z component of a vector property</value>
      <value name="VectorW">Bind to the W component of a vector property</value>
    </enum>
    <enum name="AnimationMode">
      <summary>Defines how an animation clip repeats after reaching its end.</summary>
      <value name="PlayOnce">Play the animation once and stop at the last frame</value>
      <value name="Loop">Restart from the beginning when the animation reaches the end</value>
      <value name="PingPong">Alternate between playing forward and backward</value>
    </enum>
    <enum name="PlaybackMode">
      <summary>Animation playback behavior modes</summary>
      <value name="Normal">Standard forward playback</value>
      <value name="Reverse">Reverse playback from end to start</value>
      <value name="PingPong">Alternating forward/reverse playback</value>
    </enum>
    <enum name="InterpolationMode">
      <value name="Linear">Linear interpolation</value>
      <value name="Const">Constant interpolation</value>
      <value name="Back">Back interpolation</value>
      <value name="Bounce">Bounce interpolation</value>
      <value name="Circ">Circular interpolation</value>
      <value name="Cubic">Cubic interpolation</value>
      <value name="Elastic">Elastic interpolation</value>
      <value name="Expo">Exponential interpolation</value>
      <value name="Quad">Quadratic interpolation</value>
      <value name="Quart">Quartic interpolation</value>
      <value name="Quint">Quintic interpolation</value>
      <value name="Sine">Sine interpolation</value>
    </enum>
    <enum name="Easing">
      <summary>Defines easing functions for animation interpolation.</summary>
      <value name="InOut">Easing function that starts slow, speeds up in the middle, and slows down at the end</value>
      <value name="In">Easing function that starts slow and speeds up towards the end</value>
      <value name="Out">Easing function that starts fast and slows down towards the end</value>
    </enum>
  </enums>
  <structs>
    <struct name="AnimationClipReference" sealed="true">
      <summary>A named animation clip entry used in an AnimationPlayer's Clips array.</summary>
      <details>Pairs a short identifying name with an AnimationClip object so that a single AnimationPlayer can hold a library of clips and play any of them by name.</details>
      <fields>
        <field name="Name" type="string">Short name used to identify and select this clip (e.g. "idle", "walk")</field>
        <field name="Clip" type="AnimationClip" pointer="true">The AnimationClip object for this entry</field>
      </fields>
    </struct>
    <struct name="Keyframe" sealed="true">
      <summary>A single keyframe in an animation curve.</summary>
      <fields>
        <field name="time" type="float">Time position of this keyframe in seconds</field>
        <field name="value" type="vec4">Animated value (up to 4 components for vectors/colors)</field>
        <field name="inSlope" type="vec4">Incoming tangent slope for bezier interpolation</field>
        <field name="outSlope" type="vec4">Outgoing tangent slope for bezier interpolation</field>
        <field name="inWeight" type="vec4">Incoming tangent weight for weighted bezier interpolation</field>
        <field name="outWeight" type="vec4">Outgoing tangent weight for weighted bezier interpolation</field>
        <field name="tangentMode" type="int">Interpolation mode for this keyframe (free, auto, linear, constant)</field>
        <field name="weightedMode" type="int">Whether tangent weights are used for this keyframe</field>
      </fields>
    </struct>
  </structs>
  <interfaces>
    <interface name="Object" prefix="OBJ_" export="Object" no-check="true">
      <summary>Core engine host object.</summary>
      <details>
        <p>The `Object` type is the root of the runtime type system. Every element that can appear in a scene, be manipulated through scripts, or participate in rendering and logic derives its basic functionality from Object. It establishes the fundamental contract that all other types extend, providing common lifecycle methods, hierarchy management, and component composition.</p>
        <p>An `Object` is not tied to a specific visual or logical role by itself. Instead, it serves as a container for components, and these components define the actual capabilities of the instance. Higher-level types such as `Node`, `Node2D`, or `ImageView` are constructed by layering specialized components on top of the base `Object`.</p>
      </details>
      <methods>
        <topic title="Lifecycle">Manages object creation, initialization, update cycles, and destruction.</topic>
        <method name="CreateFromLuaState" export="new" lua="true" static="true">
          <summary>Create new object.</summary>
          <details>This is a fall through constructor, that you can pass a table of properties to</details>
          <returns type="nresults"/>
        </method>
        <method name="Awake" lua="true">
          <summary>Initializes the core component when it is loaded, an essential lifecycle method.</summary>
          <details>Perform setup and dependency wiring here before other logic runs.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="Animate" lua="true">
          <summary>Runs object animations.</summary>
          <details>Invokes the animation pipeline for this object and its hierarchy.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="Clear" export="clear" lua="true">
          <summary>Clear all children of the object.</summary>
          <details>Removes and properly releases all child objects from this object's hierarchy. This operation recursively clears each child object, removes them from the parent-child relationship, unreferences their Lua objects, and sets their parent pointer to NULL. The children list is then cleared. This is a destructive operation that completely empties the object's child hierarchy.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="Release" export="__gc" lua="true">
          <summary>Garbage-collect an object (clear and release).</summary>
          <details>Performs complete cleanup and destruction of the object. This includes: clearing all children recursively, removing the object from its parent's children list, clearing game focus/hover references if this object holds them, sending a "Destroy" message, releasing animation libraries, timers, animations, style classes, components, properties, and aliases. Finally frees all allocated memory including SourceFile, TextContent, Name, ClassName, and Xmlns strings. This is the final cleanup method called during garbage collection.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="Equals" const="true" export="__eq">
          <summary>Compare two objects for equality.</summary>
          <details>Compares this object with another object to determine if they represent the same instance. Typically implemented as pointer comparison or unique identifier matching to determine object identity rather than content equality.</details>
          <arg name="other" type="Object" pointer="true" const="true">The second object to compare against this object for equality</arg>
          <returns type="bool">True if the objects are the same instance, false if they are different objects</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="Rebuild" lua="true">
          <summary>Rebuilds the object's body content asynchronously</summary>
          <details>This method triggers a rebuild of the behavior by either executing a function body, adding a child from a string, and then posting a 'ViewDidLoad' message.</details>
        </method>
        <topic title="Hierarchy">Navigates and manipulates the parent-child relationship tree.</topic>
        <method name="AddChild">
          <summary>Add a child object.</summary>
          <details>Adds the specified object as a child of this object in the hierarchy. If the child already has a parent, it is first removed from that parent's children list using REMOVE_FROM_LIST. The child is then added to the end of this object's children list and its parent pointer is set to this object. An "Attached" message is sent to the newly added child. If is_template is true, the OF_TEMPLATE flag is set on this object to indicate it contains template children.</details>
          <arg name="child" type="Object" pointer="true">The child object to add to this object's hierarchy</arg>
          <arg name="is_template" type="bool">If true, marks this object with the OF_TEMPLATE flag to indicate it contains template children</arg>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Returns added child object, for chaining calls</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="RemoveFromParent" lua="true">
          <summary>Destroys an object.</summary>
          <details>Detaches object form it's parent that causes the object to be garbage collected.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="GetParent" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the parent object in the hierarchy</summary>
          <details>Returns a pointer to the parent object, or null if this is the root object.</details>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to parent object, or null if no parent</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetFirstChild" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the first child object</summary>
          <details>Returns a pointer to the first child in the object hierarchy, or null if no children exist.</details>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to first child object, or null if no children</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetNext" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the next sibling object</summary>
          <details>Returns a pointer to the next sibling object at the same hierarchy level, or null if this is the last sibling.</details>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to next sibling object, or null if no next sibling</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetRoot">
          <summary>Gets the root object of the hierarchy</summary>
          <details>Traverses up the parent chain to find and return the topmost object in the hierarchy.</details>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to root object</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindChild">
          <summary>Find a child object by name.</summary>
          <details>Searches for a child object with the specified name. When recursive is false, only searches immediate children. When recursive is true, performs a depth-first search through the entire subtree to find the first object with a matching name. The search compares against the object's Name property using string comparison.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">The exact name of the child object to locate</arg>
          <arg name="recursive" type="bool">If true, searches recursively through all descendants; if false, searches only immediate children</arg>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to the first child object found with the matching name, or null if no match is found</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindByPath">
          <summary>Finds child object by hierarchical path</summary>
          <details>Searches through object hierarchy using a path string (e.g., "parent/child/grandchild") to locate nested objects.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">Hierarchical path to the target object</arg>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to found object, or null if not found</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindChildByID">
          <summary>Finds a child object by its unique identifier</summary>
          <details>Searches through child objects to find one matching the specified ID.</details>
          <arg name="id" type="uint">Unique identifier of the child object to find</arg>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to child object with matching ID, or null if not found</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindChildByAlias">
          <summary>Finds a child object by its alias identifier</summary>
          <details>Searches through child objects to find one matching the specified alias ID.</details>
          <arg name="id" type="uint">Alias identifier of the child object to find</arg>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to child object with matching alias, or null if not found</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindChildOfClass">
          <summary>Finds a child object of a specific class</summary>
          <details>Searches the children of this object to find the first child that matches the specified class identifier. The search can be recursive depending on implementation.  This is useful for locating specific UI elements within a container, such as finding a button within a panel.  Returns null if no matching child is found.</details>
          <arg name="classID" type="uint">The hashed identifier of the class to search for</arg>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to the matching child object, or null if not found</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindParentOfClass">
          <summary>Finds the nearest parent object of a specific class</summary>
          <details>Traverses up the object hierarchy starting from this object to find the first parent that matches the specified class identifier. This is useful for finding containing elements, such as finding the parent window or panel that contains a button.  Returns null if no matching parent is found.</details>
          <arg name="classID" type="uint">The hashed identifier of the class to search for</arg>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to the matching parent object, or null if not found</returns>
        </method>
        <topic title="Messaging">Dispatches events and sends messages between objects.</topic>
        <method name="post" lua="true">
          <summary>Posts a message asynchronously, bubbling through the object hierarchy.</summary>
          <details>Places a message on the global queue for asynchronous processing. The message bubbles up through the parent chain until a handler claims it. Does not return a value.</details>
          <arg name="message" type="string">The name of the message to post</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="send" lua="true">
          <summary>Sends a message synchronously to the current object and returns the result.</summary>
          <details>Dispatches a message directly to this object's components without bubbling. Returns the LRESULT from the first component that handles the message as an integer, or nil if unhandled (LRESULT == 0).</details>
          <arg name="message" type="string">The name of the message to send</arg>
          <returns type="nresults">The LRESULT as integer, or nil if unhandled</returns>
        </method>
        <topic title="Properties">Reads and writes typed properties, applying and observing changes.</topic>
        <method name="SetProperty" export="__setproperty" lua="true">
          <summary>Set a property on the object.</summary>
          <details>Sets or updates a named property on this object. If the property doesn't exist, it may be created. If it exists, its value is updated. This method integrates with the Lua property system and may trigger property change callbacks and validation. The property system supports various data types including primitives, vectors, colors, and custom types.</details>
          <arg name="Property" type="string">The name of the property to set or update</arg>
          <returns type="bool">True if the property was successfully set, false if the operation failed due to invalid property name, type mismatch, or other constraints</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetProperty" export="__getproperty" lua="true">
          <summary>Get a property value from an object.</summary>
          <details>Retrieves the current value of the specified property from this object. The method searches through the object's property collection and returns the value if found. If the property doesn't exist, returns nil. This integrates with Lua's property access system and supports all property data types including handles, floats, vectors, colors, integers, booleans, and enumerations.</details>
          <arg name="Property" type="string">The name of the property whose value to retrieve</arg>
          <returns type="nresults">The current value of the property, or nil if the property doesn't exist. Return type varies based on property data type</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="UpdateProperties">
          <summary>Updates object properties.</summary>
          <details>Applies property changes and recalculates dependent state.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="EmitPropertyChangedEvents" lua="true">
          <summary>Emits onPropertyChanged events by comparing to previous values.</summary>
          <details>Ensures attached state manager (if any) is initialized and goes through properties seeking for changes to fire on-changed events. Recursively goes through children.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="FindImplicitProperty">
          <summary>Looks up a property by context-driven syntax, like "Column" instead of "Grid.Column"</summary>
          <details>Searches for a property using a context-driven approach, allowing shorthand notation for commonly used properties. This method simplifies property access by inferring the full property path based on the current context.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">The name of the property to find</arg>
          <returns type="PropertyType" pointer="true" const="true">Pointer to a property type, null if not found</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindExplicitProperty">
          <summary>Looks up a property by full syntax, like "Grid.Column" instead of "Column"</summary>
          <details>Searches for a property using the full property path, requiring the complete syntax for accurate identification. This method ensures precise property access by using the explicit path provided.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">The full name of the property to find</arg>
          <returns type="PropertyType" pointer="true" const="true">Pointer to a property type, null if not found</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="AttachPropertyProgram">
          <summary>Attaches a property program to the specified property</summary>
          <details>Enables attaching custom programs to bindings to perform calculations and transformations on bound data. For example, multiplying a DataSource value: DataSource.Speed * 20. The attached program is evaluated whenever the source data changes, allowing for dynamic property updates based on complex expressions. This allows for complex binding expressions and dynamic property computation without requiring explicit code-behind logic.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">The full name of the property to attach the program to</arg>
          <arg name="program" type="string">The program or expression to attach to the property</arg>
          <arg name="attribute" type="PropertyAttribute">The attribute of the property to attach the program to (e.g., Value, Color, etc.)</arg>
          <arg name="mode" type="BindingMode">The binding mode for the property program (e.g., OneWay, TwoWay, OneWayToSource)</arg>
          <arg name="enabled" type="bool">Whether the property program is enabled</arg>
          <returns type="bool">True if the property program was successfully attached, false otherwise</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="FindPropertyByPath">
          <summary>Finds a property by navigating a hierarchical path</summary>
          <details>Traverses the object hierarchy following the specified path and returns the property at the end.  The path uses forward slashes to navigate through child objects, ending with a property name (e.g., "Child1/Child2/PropertyName"). This allows accessing properties on descendant objects without manually traversing each level.  Returns null if any part of the path is not found or if the final element is not a valid property. </details>
          <arg name="path" type="string">Slash-separated path to the property (e.g., "Child1/Child2/PropertyName")</arg>
          <returns type="Property" pointer="true">Pointer to the property if found, or null if the path is invalid</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetProperties" const="true" private="true">
          <summary>Gets the properties collection</summary>
          <details>Returns a pointer to the property collection containing configuration and state data for this object.</details>
          <returns type="Property" pointer="true">Pointer to properties collection</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetInteger" const="true">
          <summary>Gets an integer property value by identifier</summary>
          <details>Searches the object's properties for a property matching the specified long identifier and returns its value as an integer. The long identifier is a fully qualified property identifier in the form ObjectClass.PropertyName (e.g., Button.Content, TextBlock.Text). The property must be of type Int, Enum, or Bool to be successfully retrieved.   If no matching property is found, or if the property type is incompatible, the fallback value is returned instead. </details>
          <arg name="ident" type="uint">The hashed long identifier "ObjectClass.PropertyName" of the property to retrieve</arg>
          <arg name="fallback" type="int">The value to return if the property is not found or incompatible</arg>
          <returns type="int">The property value if found and compatible, otherwise the fallback value</returns>
        </method>
        <topic title="Layout">Controls position, size, and dirty-flag propagation for layout passes.</topic>
        <method name="SetDirty">
          <summary>Sets object dirty and queues it for recalculation</summary>
          <details>Marks the object as needing recalculation and updates the timestamp. Dirty objects are processed during the next update cycle to ensure consistent state.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="ClearDirtyFlags">
          <summary>Clears dirty flags, marks object as recalculated</summary>
          <details>Resets the dirty state of the object, indicating that it has been recalculated and no further updates are needed until it becomes dirty again.</details>
        </method>
        <topic title="Style">Manages style sheets and resolves computed style values.</topic>
        <method name="AddStyleRule" lua="true">
          <summary>Add a stylesheet to the object.</summary>
          <details>Attaches a stylesheet resource to this object, enabling rule-based styling capabilities. The stylesheet contains rules that can modify the appearance and behavior of this object and potentially its children. Stylesheets support selectors, property assignments, and cascading rules. Multiple stylesheets can be applied to the same object, with later sheets taking precedence for conflicting rules.</details>
          <arg name="source" type="string">Name or path of the stylesheet resource to load and apply to this object</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="GetStyle" const="true">
          <summary>Retrieves object style flags</summary>
          <details>Returns a bitmask of style flags similar to WinAPI style constants. Each bit represents different visual or behavioral properties.</details>
          <returns type="uint">Current style flags as bitmask</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetStyle">
          <summary>Sets object style flags</summary>
          <details>Applies a bitmask of style flags to control object appearance and behavior. Flags can be combined using bitwise OR operations like WinAPI styles.</details>
          <arg name="style" type="uint">Style flags bitmask to apply</arg>
        </method>
        <topic title="Animation">Attaches, plays, and transitions keyframe animations on this object.</topic>
        <method name="DoTween" lua="true">
          <summary>Tween an object property over time.</summary>
          <details>Creates and initiates a smooth animation transition (tween) that interpolates an object property from its current value to a target value over a specified duration. Supports various easing functions and animation curves. The tween system handles different property types including scalars, vectors, and colors. Multiple tweens can run simultaneously on different properties of the same object.</details>
          <arg name="property" type="string">Property to tween</arg>
          <arg name="duration" type="int">Duration of the tween in seconds</arg>
          <arg name="ipo" type="InterpolationMode">Interpolation mode for the tween</arg>
          <arg name="easing" type="Easing">Easing function for the tween</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="AddComponentByName" lua="true">
          <summary>Attaches a component class to this object.</summary>
          <details>Adds the component identified by the given class name to this object's component list. The component's properties become immediately accessible on the object. Useful for dynamically composing behaviour at runtime, e.g. attaching an AnimationPlayer or Trigger to an existing node.</details>
          <arg name="className" type="string">The class name of the component to attach (e.g. "AnimationPlayer")</arg>
        </method>
        <topic title="Focus and Input">Controls focus state, hover, modal presentation, and timers.</topic>
        <method name="SetFocus">
          <summary>Set focus on the object.</summary>
          <details>Makes this object the currently focused object in the game interface. This triggers focus change events: sends "KillFocus" to the previously focused object (if any) and "SetFocus" to this object. Also posts "ThemeChanged" messages to both objects to update their visual appearance. Updates the game's global focus reference to point to this object.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="IsFocused" const="true">
          <summary>Checks if this object currently has focus</summary>
          <details>Returns true if this object is currently the focused object in the game interface, false otherwise. The focused object typically receives keyboard input and visual focus indicators.</details>
          <returns type="bool">True if this object has focus, false otherwise</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetHover">
          <summary>Sets the hover state for an object</summary>
          <details>Marks this object as the currently hovered object. This is typically called by the input system when the mouse cursor moves over an object.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="ShowModal" lua="true">
          <summary>Sets or clears the modal child object</summary>
          <details>Sets a child object as modal, or clears the existing modal by passing null. When set, the previous modal is removed from the parent and the new modal object is attached. The modal object has the OF_NOACTIVATE flag set and its parent pointer is updated. Modal objects are typically used for popups, menus, or dialogs that should capture input.</details>
          <arg name="modal" type="Object" pointer="true">The object to set as modal, or null to clear the current modal</arg>
          <returns type="nresults">Starts a coroutine</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetTimer">
          <summary>Set a timer on the object.</summary>
          <details>Creates and starts a timer associated with this object. Timers can be one-shot or repeating, and execute callback functions after specified delays or intervals. The timer is automatically cleaned up when the object is destroyed. Multiple timers can be active on the same object simultaneously. Timers integrate with the game's update loop and respect pause states.</details>
          <arg name="duration" type="int">Duration of the timer in milliseconds</arg>
          <returns type="int">Handle or identifier for the created timer, which can be used to control or cancel the timer before it expires</returns>
        </method>
        <topic title="Identity and State">Accesses name, class, flags, aliases, text content, and Lua state.</topic>
        <method name="GetName" const="true">
          <summary>Retrieves the object's name identifier</summary>
          <details>Returns the string name assigned to this object instance for identification and lookup purposes.</details>
          <returns type="string">Current name of the object</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetName">
          <summary>Sets the object's name identifier</summary>
          <details>Assigns a new name to this object for identification. Names are typically used for hierarchical lookups and debugging.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">New name to assign to the object</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="GetClassName" const="true">
          <summary>Returns the object's class type name</summary>
          <details>Retrieves the runtime type information for this object, useful for type checking and reflection.</details>
          <returns type="string">Class name of the object type</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetClassName">
          <summary>Sets the class name of the object</summary>
          <details>Assigns a class name to this object. The class name can be used for styling, identification, or querying objects with similar characteristics. This enables flexible categorization and styling of UI elements without relying solely on object types.</details>
          <arg name="classID" type="string">The class name to assign to the object</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="CheckName" const="true">
          <summary>Checks if object has a specific name</summary>
          <details>Performs name comparison to determine if this object matches the given identifier.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">Name to check against</arg>
          <returns type="bool">True if object name matches the provided string</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetFlags" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the object flags</summary>
          <details>Returns the bitfield representing the current state of the object.</details>
          <returns type="uint">Bitfield of object flags</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetFlags">
          <summary>Sets the object flags</summary>
          <details>Updates the bitfield representing the object's state. Only the flags marked as user-settable in the documentation should be modified directly.</details>
          <arg name="flags" type="uint">New bitfield value for the object flags</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="GetIdentifier" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the identifier of the object</summary>
          <details>Returns the unique identifier of this object. The identifier is a hash of the object's name and remains stable across sessions for consistent reference.</details>
          <returns type="uint">Hashed identifier of the object</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetAlias" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the alias identifier</summary>
          <details>Returns the alias ID of the object if one is defined.</details>
          <returns type="uint">Alias identifier</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetSourceFile" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the source file path</summary>
          <details>Returns the file path of the source file from which this object was created or loaded.</details>
          <returns type="string">Path to the source file</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetSourceFile">
          <summary>Sets the source file path of the object</summary>
          <details>Associates a source file path with this object, typically used for debugging purposes or to track which file defined the object. This is useful when loading UI elements from external files or templates to maintain a reference to the original source location.</details>
          <arg name="path" type="string">The file path to associate with the object</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="GetTextContent" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the text content of the object</summary>
          <details>Returns the textual content contained within this object, if applicable.</details>
          <returns type="string">Text content of the object</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetTextContent">
          <summary>Sets the text content of the object</summary>
          <details>Updates the text content displayed by this object. This is typically used for text labels, buttons, or other UI elements that display text.  The text content is copied internally and can be modified at any time to update the displayed text.</details>
          <arg name="text" type="string">The text content to display</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="GetTimestamp" const="true">
          <summary>Gets the last modified timestamp</summary>
          <details>Returns the timestamp of when this object was last marked dirty, indicating the last time it required recalculation.</details>
          <returns type="long">Timestamp of last dirty marking</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetLuaObject" const="true" private="true">
          <summary>Gets the Lua object reference</summary>
          <details>Returns the Lua registry index associated with this object.</details>
          <returns type="uint">Lua registry index for the object</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="GetDomain">
          <summary>Gets the domain of the object</summary>
          <details>Returns the domain to which this object belongs, which can be used for organizational or scoping purposes within the engine.</details>
          <returns type="lua_State" pointer="true">The domain of the object</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="SetContext" export="__setcontext" lua="true">
          <summary>Set the current context object where newly created objects will be parented.</summary>
          <details>Establishes this object as the current creation context in the Lua environment. When new objects are created through Lua scripts without explicitly specifying a parent, they will automatically be added as children of this context object. This provides a convenient way to control object hierarchy during scripted object creation and helps maintain organized scene structures.</details>
        </method>
        <topic title="Prefabs and Aliases">Loads prefab templates and manages named child aliases.</topic>
        <method name="Instantiate" lua="true">
          <summary>Instantiates a new object from this prefab.</summary>
          <details>Will load from the source, not adding it to the static workspace hierarchy</details>
          <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Returns the instantiated object</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="LoadPrefabs" lua="true">
          <summary>Loads and instantiates prefabs.</summary>
          <details>Resolves and loads prefab resources for this object tree.</details>
        </method>
        <method name="IsPrefabView" const="true">
          <summary>Checks if this object is a prefab view container</summary>
          <details>Returns true if this object is a PrefabView, which is a special container that can dynamically load and instantiate different prefab templates based on its source property. Similar to Kanzi's PrefabView, this allows for runtime loading of reusable UI component templates by changing the source string, making it useful for dynamic UI composition and template-based layouts.</details>
          <returns type="bool">True if this object is a PrefabView, false otherwise</returns>
        </method>
        <method name="AddAlias">
          <summary>Registers an alias for a child object path</summary>
          <details>Adds a named alias that provides a shorthand reference to a child object path. This is called during the loading phase to register aliases.  Once registered, the aliased path can be referenced using the syntax #AliasName/Child/Property instead of the full path Full/Path/Child/Property.  Aliases simplify references to frequently accessed objects and make UI definitions more maintainable.</details>
          <arg name="name" type="string">The alias name (used as #name in references)</arg>
          <arg name="path" type="string">The full path to the object being aliased</arg>
        </method>
        <method name="AssignAliases">
          <summary>Resolves and assigns all registered aliases for an object</summary>
          <details>Called after the loading phase to resolve alias references and assign aliased children to internal structures. This compilation step processes all aliases registered via AddAlias and updates internal pointers to the actual objects referenced by the given path. This ensures that alias references like #AliasName/Child/Property are properly resolved and ready for use at runtime.</details>
          <arg name="pathToObject" type="string">The path to the object being processed for alias resolution</arg>
        </method>
      </methods>
      <messages>
        <message name="Create">
          <summary>Sent once when the component is first created and attached to an object.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Start">
          <summary>Sent after the entire object hierarchy has been loaded, signalling that the scene is ready for logic execution.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Animate">
          <summary>Requested when an animation update is needed.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="ThemeChanged">
          <summary>Sent when the active theme is changed, allowing components to refresh their styled resources.</summary>
          <fields>
            <field name="recursive" type="bool">Whether to propagate the theme change to child objects</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
        <message name="PropertyChanged">
          <summary>Sent when a property value on the object changes.</summary>
          <fields>
            <field name="Property" type="Property" pointer="true">The property that changed</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
        <message name="Attached">
          <summary>Sent when the object is attached to a parent object in the hierarchy.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Release">
          <summary>Sent when the object is being released and its resources should be freed.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Destroy">
          <summary>Sent just before the object is destroyed and removed from the scene.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Timer">
          <summary>Sent on each timer tick registered for this object.</summary>
          <fields>
            <field name="timerId" type="int">Timer identifier returned by setTimer</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
      </messages>
    </interface>
  </interfaces>
  <classes>
    <class name="AnimationCurve">
      <summary>A single animated property curve, consisting of keyframes for one property on one target object.</summary>
      <details>AnimationCurve is a standalone object that describes how a single property on a target object changes over time. It holds an array of Keyframe values and is typically created as a child of an AnimationClip object.</details>
      <properties>
        <property name="Path" type="string">Relative path from the AnimationClip's host object to the target object (empty string means the host object itself)</property>
        <property name="Property" type="string">Short name of the property to animate (e.g. "Opacity", "Position")</property>
        <property name="Keyframes" type="Keyframe" array="true">Array of keyframes that define this curve</property>
      </properties>
    </class>
    <class name="AnimationClip">
      <summary>A reusable, self-loading animation asset containing one or more AnimationCurve components.</summary>
      <details>AnimationClip is an object class (like Image or Shader) that loads itself from XML. Each child AnimationCurve component describes how one property changes over time. Once loaded, an AnimationClip can be referenced by an AnimationPlayer component via its Clip property. ANIM_Load is no longer needed — simply load the clip's XML file with require().</details>
      <handles>
        <handle message="Object.Start"/>
      </handles>
      <properties>
        <property name="Mode" type="AnimationMode">Playback mode: PlayOnce stops at end, Loop restarts, PingPong alternates direction</property>
        <property name="StartTime" type="float">Start time of the active region in seconds (default 0)</property>
        <property name="StopTime" type="float">End time of the active region in seconds</property>
      </properties>
    </class>
    <class name="AnimationPlayer" attach-only="true">
      <summary>Component for managing and playing animations on UI elements.</summary>
      <details>AnimationPlayer is an attach-only component that drives keyframe animation on the object it is attached to. Attach it to any node with addComponent("AnimationPlayer") or as an XML child element. Set the Clip property to an AnimationClip object, then set Playing=true (or send the Play message) to start playback. The component advances CurrentTime each frame when it receives the Object.Animate message and evaluates all AnimationCurves in the clip.</details>
      <handles>
        <handle message="Object.Start"/>
        <handle message="Object.Animate"/>
        <handle message="AnimationPlayer.Play"/>
        <handle message="AnimationPlayer.Resume"/>
        <handle message="AnimationPlayer.Stop"/>
        <handle message="AnimationPlayer.Pause"/>
      </handles>
      <properties>
        <property name="Clip" type="AnimationClip" pointer="true">The AnimationClip object that supplies the curves to animate</property>
        <property name="Clips" type="AnimationClipReference" array="true">Array of named animation clips available to this player; use the Play message with a Name to select one by name</property>
        <property name="Playing" type="bool">Whether the animation is currently advancing each frame</property>
        <property name="Looping" type="bool">If true, the animation restarts from StartTime when it reaches StopTime</property>
        <property name="Speed" type="float" default="1.0">Playback speed multiplier (1.0 = normal speed)</property>
        <property name="CurrentTime" type="float">Current playback position within the animation in seconds</property>
        <property name="AutoplayEnabled" type="bool">Enables or disables automatic playback on initialization.</property>
        <property name="RelativePlayback" type="bool">When true, playback is relative to the current state rather than starting from an absolute base state.</property>
        <property name="RestoreOriginalValuesAfterPlayback" type="bool">Restores the original property values after the animation ends.</property>
        <property name="PlaybackMode" type="PlaybackMode">Defines how the animation should be played.</property>
        <property name="DurationScale" type="float">Scales the playback speed of the animation. A value greater than 1.0 speeds up playback, while values between 0.0 and 1.0 slow it down.</property>
        <property name="RepeatCount" type="int">Number of times the animation should repeat. Use -1 to indicate infinite looping.</property>
      </properties>
      <fields>
        <field name="_prevRealtime" type="long">The last real time when the animation was updated, used to calculate delta time for advancing CurrentTime</field>
      </fields>
      <messages>
        <message name="Play">
          <summary>Starts or resumes animation playback.</summary>
          <fields>
            <field name="Name" type="string">Name of the clip to play (optional; if set, selects a clip from the Clips array before starting)</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
        <message name="Resume">
          <summary>Resumes animation playback from the current position without resetting.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Stop">
          <summary>Stops animation playback and resets CurrentTime to the clip's StartTime.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Pause">
          <summary>Pauses animation playback without resetting CurrentTime.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Started">
          <summary>Sent when animation playback begins.</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Stopped">
          <summary>Sent when animation playback stops (via Stop or Pause).</summary>
        </message>
        <message name="Completed">
          <summary>Sent when animation playback reaches the end of the clip without looping.</summary>
        </message>
      </messages>
    </class>
    <class name="PropertyAnimation" attach-only="true">
      <summary>Attach-only component that tweens one property value to a target, then self-destructs.</summary>
      <details>Created internally by OBJ_DoTween (the Lua animate method). Advances a single property from a captured start value to the target value over the specified duration using the chosen easing curve, then removes itself from the object.</details>
      <handles>
        <handle message="Object.Animate"/>
      </handles>
      <properties>
        <property name="Property" type="string">Property to animate</property>
	      <property name="From" type="string">Start value (raw bytes)</property>
	      <property name="To" type="string">End value (raw bytes)</property>
        <property name="Interpolation" type="InterpolationMode">Interpolation method</property>
        <property name="Easing" type="Easing">Easing function</property>
        <property name="Start" type="int">Timestamp when animation started</property>
        <property name="Duration" type="int">Duration in milliseconds</property>
      </properties>
      <fields>
        <field name="_property" type="Property" pointer="true">The property being animated</field>
      </fields>
    </class>
    <class name="StyleController" attach-only="true">
      <summary>Manages CSS-style classes and stylesheet rules for an object.</summary>
      <details>StyleController provides CSS-like styling capabilities. Style classes (e.g., "button:hover:dark") are parsed from XML class attributes and matched against stylesheet rules. Stylesheets can be loaded from external .css files or defined inline. This component is automatically attached to Node2D and any other visual elements that support styling.</details>
      <handles>
        <handle message="Object.Create"/>
        <handle message="Object.Release"/>
        <handle message="StyleController.ThemeChanged"/>
        <handle message="StyleController.AddClass"/>
        <handle message="StyleController.AddClasses"/>
      </handles>
      <fields>
        <field name="classes" type="style_class_selector" pointer="true">Linked list of parsed style classes with flags (hover, focus, dark mode, etc.)</field>
        <field name="rules" type="style_rule" pointer="true">Linked list of style rules (selector to property to value mappings)</field>
      </fields>
      <messages>
        <message name="ThemeChanged" routing="Direct">
          <summary>Applies styles to this object.</summary>
          <details>Triggers style recalculation on this object. When recursive is TRUE, also sends ThemeChanged to every direct child. Preferred over the removed OBJ_ApplyStyles() function.</details>
          <fields>
            <field name="recursive" type="bool">When TRUE, also sends ThemeChanged to every direct child</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
        <message name="AddClass">
          <summary>Adds single styling class</summary>
          <fields>
            <field name="ClassName" type="string">Name of the class to add</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
        <message name="AddClasses">
          <summary>Adds multiple styling classes</summary>
          <fields>
            <field name="ClassNames" type="string">Space-separated list of class names to add</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
      </messages>
    </class>
    <class name="StateManagerController" attach-only="true">
      <summary>Manages XML-driven state groups that reactively apply property values when controller properties change.</summary>
      <details>StateManagerController is an attach-only component that loads a Kanzi-style StateManager XML document and evaluates its StateGroup entries whenever a tracked controller property changes value. Set the StateManager property to a file path to load and activate a state manager document transparently. The component lazily initializes its internal state group list on the first Object.Start and then dispatches ControllerChanged whenever a property marked PF_USED_IN_STATE_MANAGER is modified.</details>
      <handles>
        <handle message="Object.Create"/>
        <handle message="Object.Release"/>
        <handle message="Object.Start"/>
        <handle message="Object.PropertyChanged"/>
        <handle message="StateManagerController.Load"/>
        <handle message="StateManagerController.ControllerChanged"/>
        <handle message="StateManagerController.Reload"/>
      </handles>
      <properties>
        <property name="StateManager" type="string">Path to the StateManager XML file. Setting this property automatically loads and activates the document.</property>
      </properties>
      <fields>
        <field name="doc" type="void" pointer="true">Parsed XML document that contains the StateGroup definitions (xmlDocPtr)</field>
        <field name="stategroups" type="void" pointer="true">Linked list of resolved STATEGRP entries (PSTATEGRP)</field>
        <field name="initialized" type="bool">TRUE once the state groups have been resolved against the object's properties</field>
      </fields>
      <messages>
        <message name="Load" routing="Direct">
          <summary>Load a StateManager XML document into this component.</summary>
          <details>Replaces any previously loaded document. The old document and all resolved state groups are released before the new one is installed. Initialization is deferred until the next Object.Start or the first ControllerChanged. Pass the xmlDocPtr in wParam and the propertyParser_t in lParam.</details>
        </message>
        <message name="Reload" routing="Direct">
          <summary>Reload the StateManager XML document from the current StateManager file path.</summary>
          <details>Re-reads the file at the path stored in the StateManager property, replacing any previously loaded document and resetting all resolved state groups. Useful after the source file has been modified on disk.</details>
        </message>
        <message name="ControllerChanged" routing="Direct">
          <summary>Evaluate all state groups whose controller property matches the changed property.</summary>
          <details>Called automatically by the property event system whenever a property flagged with PF_USED_IN_STATE_MANAGER changes value. Iterates each matching StateGroup and applies the matching State's property overrides to the object tree.</details>
          <fields>
            <field name="Property" type="Property" pointer="true">The property whose value changed, triggering state group evaluation</field>
          </fields>
        </message>
      </messages>
    </class>
  </classes>
  <functions>
    <function name="GetFocus">
      <summary>Retrieves currently active object.</summary>
      <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to the currently focused object, or null if no object has focus</returns>
    </function>
    <function name="GetHover">
      <summary>Gets the currently hovered object</summary>
      <details>Returns a pointer to the object that is currently being hovered over by the mouse cursor. Returns null if no object is being hovered.</details>
      <returns type="Object" pointer="true">Pointer to the object under the mouse cursor, or null if no object is being hovered</returns>
    </function>
<!--  <function name="AddCommands" lua="true">-->
<!--    <summary>Retrieves currently active object.</summary>-->
<!--    <arg name="command" type="string"/>-->
<!--  </function>-->
  </functions>
</module>
